Welcome to the third lecture.
I hope you made good progress with
the assignment from the last session.
Our next step in becoming more
precise about our use of language for
use in mathematics is to take a close
look at the meaning of the word implies.
This turns out to be pretty tricky.
Brace yourself for
several days of confusion until the idea
sought themselves out in your mind.
Just like learning to ride a bike.
Well, all the actual learning occurs
before you finally get the hang of it.
So too, most of the benefit
from understanding the way
our language is used in mathematics
comes from trying to figure it out.
The benefits in this case is helping
to develop your mathematical thinking
ability, and
extra process of trying to understand
the issue that goes out for you.
Yeah, sure, once you've sorted
this language stuff out,
you'll be able to use
language well actually.
But by that stage, you'll just using it,
the part that helps you with when and
how to think mathematically
is largely over.
We'll need other tasks to develop your
mathematical thinking ability forever.
So as you get into this, bear in mind
that the pay off for struggling with
issues is significant in terms of being
able to think like a mathematician.
Here we go.
In mathematics, we frequently encounter
expressions of the form, Phi implies Psi.
Indeed, implication is the means by
which we prove results in mathematics,
starting with observations or axioms.
So we'd better understand how
the word implies behaves.
In particular, how does the truth or
falsity of a statement Phi implies Psi
depend upon the truth or
falsity of Phi and of Psi?
Well, the obvious answer is to
say that Phi implies Psi if
the truth of Psi follows
from the truth of Phi.
But is that what we want?
Let me give you an example, that phi
of the statement loop 2 is a rational.
And that psi of the statement
is 0 is less than 1.
And let's ask ourselves,
is the statements phi implies psi true?
Well, phi is true.
As I've mentioned once already, we're
going to prove that later in the course.
And we all know that psi is true,
0 is certainly less than 1.
So we have the truth of this.
We have the truth of that.
Does that mean that phi implies psi?
Obviously not.
There's no relationship between phi and
psi.
This takes some effort to prove,
as you'll see.
We all know this one.
So yes, this is true and that's true, but
the truth of this doesn't
follow from the truth of that.
And now we realize there's
a complexity with implication that
we didn't meet before when we were
dealing with and, with or, and with not.
And the complexity is that implication
Involves causality.
Causality is an issue of great complexity
that philosophers have been discussing for
generations.
Now, we're facing a problem.
It didn't arise before, because when
we're dealing with conjunction and
disjunction, it didn't
matter whether there was
any kind of relationship between
the two conjuncts or the two disjuncts.
For example, let's look at the sentence,
Julius Caesar is dead,
and let's conjoin it with the sentence
1 + 1 = 3, the mathematical sentence.
And let's do the same
thing with disjunction.
Forming a conjunction and
disjunction didn't require any kind
of relationship between these two.
Clearly, they're independent.
One's a statement about
a long dead individual, and
the other one is a mathematical statement.
Incidentally, why do we
got these in front of us?
Let me just give you a quick quiz.
Is the first one true, or is it false?
Is the second one true, or is it false?
What do you think?
Well, remember what the definition was.
A conjunction is true if
both conjuncts are true.
This one's true but this one's false,
so the conjunction's false.
This one's true.
This one's false.
All that you need for
a disjunction to be true is at least
one of the disjuncts to be true.
So that one's true.
And the fact that there's no
meaningful relationship between the two
conjuncts in this case, or
the two disjuncts in that case,
created no lull in determining
what the truth value was.
It was purely in terms of truth and
falsity.
But it's not sitting with implication,
because implication involves causality.
So let me just express that explicitly.
Implication has a truth part and
a causation part.
What we're going to do
is ignore that part.
We're going to leave that to the
philosophers if you like and we're just
going to focus on the truth part, now that
might sound to be a very rush thing to do.
Throwing away a causation, now,
we can't be left with anything useful, but
it turns out yeah,
it might seem a dangerous thing to do,
to throw away this important causation
implication, but it turns out when we
focus on the truth part we are left with
enough to save our leaves in mathematics.
So much so
that we're going to give this a name.
We're going to call it the conditional.
Or sometimes, the material conditional.
That's the part we're going to focus on.
So we're going to split implication into
two parts, conditional and causation.
The first part, the conditional,
we're going to define entirely
in terms of truth values.
And the second part we're going
to leave to the philosophers.
The symbol that we use normally for
conditional,
at least the symbol I'm going to use,
is a double arrow.
Lots of textbooks use a single arrow,
but that has many uses in mathematics,
so we certainly are going to use that for
something else later on in the course.
So to avoid confusion, I'm going to stick
to this notation for the conditional.
So I'm going to write conditional
expressions like this.
That's the truth part of phi implies psi.
When we have a conditional,
we call phi the antecedent, and
we call psi the consequent.
And we're going to formally define
the truth of phi conditional psi in
terms of the truth of phi,
and the truth of psi.
Well, you might worry that by
throwing away a causation,
we're going to be left with a notion
that's really of no use whatsoever.
That actually is not the case.
Even though we're throwing away
something of great significance,
hanging on to the truth part
leaves us something very useful.
And the reason is,
whenever we have a genuine implication,
which are actually the only
circumstances in which we're ultimately
going to be interested,
whenever we have a genuine implication,
the truth behavior of
the conditional is the correct one.
It really does capture what
happens with truth and falsity,
when we have a genuine implication.
That probably seems a bit
mysterious at this stage, but
when we start to look at some examples, I
think it should become clear what I mean.
The advantage is that
the conditional is always defined.
For real implication, you've got that
issue of causation, the square root
of 2 and the 0 less than 1 example,
the truth or falsity wasn't the issue,
it was whether there was a relationship
between those two statements.
Now, that's a complicated issue.
But because we're going to
define the conditional purely in
terms of the truth value of the two
constituents, the antecedent and
the consequent, it turns out that
the conditional will always be defined.
When we do have a genuine implication,
the definition of the conditional will
agree with the way implication behaves.
And when we don't have
a genuine implication,
the conditional will still be defined,
and so we can proceed.
Again, this probably seems very mysterious
when I describe it in this way.
But as we develop some examples,
I hope you'll be able to understand
what I'm trying to get at.
Okay, I think we need
to catch our breaths.
Let me do that by giving you a quiz.
The truth of the conditional from
phi to psi is defined in terms of?
1, the truth of phi and psi, or 2,
whether phi causes psi, or both.
Which is it?
It's number 1.
We define the truth of a conditional
in terms of the truth and
falsity of the antecedents and
the consequent.
And because we define the truth of
the conditional in terms of truth and
falsity in that way, it has a truth table.
So let's see if we can
figure out what it is.
Well, the, I'm not giving you,
this is a quiz, by the way,
I'm going to work this one through.
This is tricky, we're not out of
the woods yet by any means, so
I'm going to lead you through this one.
This part we've already looked at.
We define the conditional as
the truth part of implication.
And implication has a property
that a true implication leads to a true
conclusion from a true assumption.
So because we take the conditional
from real implication,
we have to have truths all
the way throughout the top level.
Now the fun begins.
We have to fill in these three values.
And when I say fun, I mean fun.
Let's look at that first
row of the truth table.
Suppose phi is the statement
N is bigger than 7.
And suppose psi is the statement
N squared is bigger than 40.
If phi is true, in other words,
if N is bigger than 7,
then N squared is
certainly bigger than 40.
In fact, it's bigger than 40 now.
So, certainly, in this case,
phi does imply psi.
So that thing is true.
If N is bigger than 7, then N squared is
certainly bigger than 40, so that's true.
We have truth everywhere.
So this is consistent
with the truth table.
Now let's look at a different example.
Let phi be the statement our old
friend Julius Caesar is dead.
And let psi be the statement
pi is bigger than 3.
Phi is true.
Psi is true.
According to the truth table, it follows
that phi conditional psi is true.
In other words, Julius Caesar is dead,
conditional, pi is bigger than 3.
Now, if you read this as Julius Caesar
is dead implies pi bigger than 3,
then you're in a nonsensical situation.
But remember, this isn't implication, this
is just the truth part of implication.
And in terms of the truth part,
there's no problem.
That's true, that's true,
the conditional is true.
In the first example,
there is a meaningful
relationship between phi and psi.
When we know that N is bigger than 7,
then we can conclude that N squared
is certainly bigger than 40.
There's a connection between the two.
And in that case, the behavior of the
conditional is certainly consistent with
what's really going on.
In the second case,
there's no connection between the two.
The conditional is true, but
it's got nothing to do with one
thing following from the other.
The value of doing this is,
even though this has no meaning
in terms of implication,
its truth value is defined.
In both cases,
we have a well-defined truth value.
In the first case,
it's a meaningful truth value.
That does follow from that.
In the second case,
it's purely a defined truth value.
But that's not going to
cause us any problems,
because we're never going to encounter
this kind of thing in mathematics.
We encounter this kind
of thing all the time.
But we're not going to
encounter this kind of thing.
So all we've done is
we've extended a notion
to be defined under all circumstances.
And we've done it in
a way that's consistent
with the behavior we want when
something meaningful is going on.
This is actually quite common in
mathematics to extend the domain of
definition of something so
that it's always defined.
So long as it has the correct behavior,
the correct definition for
the meaningful cases, and
provided we do the definition correctly,
it really doesn't cause any problems.
In fact, it solves a lot of problems and
eliminates a lot of difficulties
if we extend the definition so
that it covers all cases.
Is it just something we do
in mathematics all the time?
May seem strange when you first meet it,
but
it is a part of modern
advanced mathematics.
Incidentally, if you think
this is just playing games,
Let me mention that the computer system
that controls that aircraft that
you'll be flying in next
time depends upon the fact
that expressions like this
are always well defined.
That software control
system doesn't depend upon
knowing whether Julius Caesar is dead or
things like that.
It doesn't depend on those
kind of facts of the world.
Computer systems, by and large,
don't depend upon understanding causation,
which is just as well, because they don't.
What computer systems depend upon is
that things are always accurately and
precisely defined.
And this expression,
phi conditional psi occurs all over
the place in software systems.
So, quite literally,
your life depends upon the fact
that this is always well-defined.
It doesn't depend upon the fact that
the computer doesn't know whether
Julius Caesar is dead or not.
Okay, time to look at the second
row of the truth table.
What goes in here, T or F?
Well we've only got two to choose from.
I guess we could just make a guess but
we're not going to do that,
we're going to figure it out and
get the right answer.
Well, what would happen
if we put a T here.
Let me put it in very lightly,
because I'm sure it's going to be a T.
If this were true,
when we think about it in terms of genuine
implication, because we are trying to
capture the truth behavior with
genuine implication, remember.
So if it was the case that
phi really did imply psi.
If that statement was true when we
interpret it as real implication
then the truth of psi would
follow from the truth of phi.
That's how we began remember.
That's what real implication means,
real implication means the truth of this
would follow from the truth of that.
So if that were a T, and
it was real implication,
then when we have a T here,
we would have to have a T there.
But we don't, we've got an F.
So we can't have a T here,
because if we put a T here the conditional
is contrary, it contradicts real
implication and we're trying to extend
implication to be defined in all
cases where there's no causation.
So this has to be an F.
If we put a T there we're in trouble.
Our notion doesn't agree
with real implication.
In order that the conditional agrees with
real implication, that has to be an F.
It's if a truth, then we would have
a true antecedent and a false
consequence from a true implication.
So we've argued backwards to
conclude that this has to be F.
Let me write that down just to make
sure everyone's following what I'm
trying to say.
If there were a genuine
implication phi implies psi and
if that implication were true,
then psi would have to be true.
If phi were true.
So we cannot have phi true and
psi false, if phi implies psi is true.
That means,
that in the case where phi is true.
And psi is false,
we have to have a false here.
Let me write that down.
Are you confused?
This is tricky.
There's no getting around the fact
that sorting out implications and
then extracting conditional
form implications is tricky.
You're probably going to have to
replay the videos several times and
look at what's been written and
think about it in order to sort this out.
I remember when I first met this, it took
me quite a while to get on top of it.
It really isn't an easy thing to do.
So, you certainly have my sympathy
that you're going to have to
struggle with this thing.
It's probably one of the hardest
things in the course,
to really come to terms with the way we
define the meaning of the conditional.
Okay, final straight.
Let's see if we can fill in the last
two entries in the truth table for
the conditional.
When we've done that, we'll all
go off in search of some aspirin.
Now if you're like me, you have no
intuitions as to what to put here.
And the reason you have no
intuition is that even though
you're used to dealing with implication
you've never dealt with an implication
where the antecedent was false.
You're only ever interested in drawing
conclusions from true assumptions.
So you never dealt with
a true one of these guys.
When this guy was false.
You don't have any intuitions.
You do however have
intuitions about this guy.
And the reason that's going to help us out
is that negation, swaps around F and T.
So corresponding to the Fs here, when
we look at this guy we'll have truths.
We'll have Ts for this.
So you are used to having
to deal with this.
When this is true,
and that will be equivalent to
dealing with this when that's false.
Because negation swaps truth and falsity.
So the trick, or at least the idea by
which we're going to figure out what goes
here, is to stop looking
at implication and
look at not implication.
Phi does not imply psi if
even though phi is true,
psi is nevertheless false.
Just think about that for
a minute, phi does not imply psi
if even though phi is true
psi is nevertheless false.
That's how you know that this guy holds.
You know that phi doesn't imply psi
if you can check that phi is true but
psi is nevertheless false.
That's the only circumstance under which
you can conclude this thing is true.
In all other circumstances,
this guy will be false.
So let me write that down.
Okay?
This guy is true if you have phi true and
psi false.
In all other circumstances,
this guy will be false.
You still with me?
Because we're only one line
away from the conclusion now.
Let me just, Rewrite that as follows.
Because negation swaps F and T,
this guy will be false,
and this guy is true.
So if we have T and F, which we have here.
Then negation is false,
which means this guy is true.
In all other circumstances,
this guy is true, so those are true.
And we're done.
Phew, that was difficult.
In fact, in my mind, this is the most
difficult part of the entire course.
This is not easy stuff,
it's going to take you some time
before you sort it out in your mind.
You're going to have to
keep working at this.
Look through the lecture several times and
think about it.
It will take effort, but you'll get there.
We all get there in the end,
but it's just not easy.
In the meantime, you've got this far.
We should start thinking about
opening a bottle of champagne.
But before you crack open the bottle, let
me leave you with one more little quiz.
Which of the following are true?
Phi conditional psi is true whenever,
(1) Phi and psi are both true.
(2) Phi is false and psi is true.
(3) Phi and psi are both false.
And (4), phi is true and psi is false.
And I want you to check all that are true.
Well, which of these four, Are the case?
Which of these four conditions
tell you when phi, psi is true?
The answer is 1, 2, and 3.
Phi conditional psi is true
either when 1 is true, or
when 2 is true, or when 3 is true.
The only time when phi conditional
psi is false is when 4 holds.
So the correct answer is 1,
2, and 3, and 4 is not.
Okay, now you can open that champagne.
Let me sum up what we've done.
We've defined a notion, the conditional,
that captures only part
of what implies means.
To avoid difficulties,
we base our definition solely on
the notion of truth and falsity.
Our definition agrees with our
intuition concerning implication in
all meaningful cases.
The definition for a true antecedent
is based on an analysis of the truth
values of genuine implication.
The definition for our false antecedents
is based on a truth value analysis
of the notion does not imply.
In defining the conditional the way we do,
we do not end up with a notion that
contradicts a notion of
genuine implication.
Rather, we obtain a notion that
extends genuine implication
to cover those cases where the claim
of implication is irrelevant,
because the antecedent is false or
meaningless
when there's no real connection between
the antecedent and the consequence.
In the meaningful case where there is
a relationship between phi and psi, and
in addition, where phi is true, namely,
the cases covered by the first two rows
of the truth table, the truth value of
the conditional will be the same as
the truth value of the actual implication.
Remember, it's the fact that
the conditional always has
a well-defined truth value that makes this
notion important in mathematics since
in mathematics,
we can't afford to have statements with
undefined truth values floating around.
Let's finish this lecture
with a short quiz.
When you've done that,
you should complete assignment three.
I've kept assignment three fairly
short since I expect you'll need most
of your time simply understanding
our analysis of implication and
the definition of the conditional.
Remember to discuss these
assignments with other students.
Don't struggle for too long on your own.
On this kind of material, it's much
more effective to work with others.
Here's the quiz.
Well, the answer to the first
one is that it's true.
The antecedent is true, and
the consequence is true, so
the conditional is true.
In fact,
there's a deeper result going on here.
Providing you take a positive number,
instead of pi,
any positive number, then if the square
of that positive number is bigger than 2,
that number must be bigger than 1.2.
Because the square root of 2 is 1.4,
etc, etc, etc.
So for positive numbers, it doesn't
have to be pi, it can be anything,
any positive number whose square is bigger
than 2, it must be bigger than 1.2.
And that would be a case of genuine
causation, genuine implication.
But in terms of the conditional,
it's enough that the antecedent is true,
then the consequence is true.
For this one, it's also true.
Now the consequence is false.
Pi certainly does not equal 3.
But the antecedent is false.
Add if you have a false antecedent,
the conditional is always true.
Pi squared is most
certainly not less than 0.
So, you've got false, false,
that makes the conditional true.
Number three, That one's false.
The antecedent is true, and
the consequence is false.
And you cannot obtain a false
conclusion from a true assumption.
What about the next one?
Well, that one's true.
The antecedent is true, and
the consequence is true.
What about this one?
Do triangles have four sides?
No.
Do squares have five sides?
But anything with a false
antecedent is true, so that's true.
You've got false, conditional,
false, and that's always true.
What about this one?
Well, we don't know when
Euclid's birthday was.
At least,
I don't know when Euclid's birthday was.
I suspect you don't either.
Rectangles certainly have four sides,
however.
Either this is true, or it's false.
Either way, since the consequence is true,
the thing is true.
We've going to run down
using the two consequence.
So either we have true, true,
in which case, it's true, or
we have false, true,
in which case, it's true.
Okay, how did you get on with that?